It's over here.
在这边
We got married seven years ago.
七年前 我们俩成为夫妻
FAMILY REGISTRY WINDOW
（户籍登记窗口）
-Excuse me. -Yes?
-打扰了 -您好
-Ichiko. -Me?
-小一 -可以吗？
Yeah.
可以
We're submitting this.
拜托您了
I'll take a look.
好的
MARRIAGE REGISTRATION NOV 22, 2017
（婚姻登记 2017年11月22日）
OTOYA AIHARA - ICHIKO YAMANE
（相原二也 山根一子）
That went pretty fast, registering our marriage.
婚姻登记好快呀
Right? We were done in about 20 seconds.
是吧？大概20秒就搞定了
Yeah.
是啊
-Ichiko. -Yeah?
小一
You don't want me to call you "The Mrs.," right?
你不想我叫你“太太”吧？
-What to call me? -Yeah.
-叫我什么？ -嗯
I don't want to say "spouse" or "bride."
我不想叫你“夫人”、“媳妇儿”什么的
So it has to be "wife," doesn't it?
所以就叫“老婆”吧？
Wife?
老婆？
Please take care of me, Wife.
请多关照 老婆
Please take care of me, Husband.
请多关照 老公
Wife.
老婆
Husband.
老公
What is it, Husband?
怎么了 老公？
Do you really not need a ring or honeymoon?
你真的不需要戒指 也不用度蜜月吗？
For now, yeah.
暂时不用
I'll probably end up losing the ring.
戒指容易弄丢
And I want to go on a trip when I feel more like taking a honeymoon.
蜜月就等到以后有了兴致再去
Okay.
好吧
This isn't in exchange,
不是作为交换
but I want to buy a condo I like.
但我想买一套中意的公寓
It doesn't need to be a brand new place,
不必是新公寓
but it should be in a convenient location,
但要位置便利
with a lot of nature and can be renovated any way I like.
绿化要好 而且要能按照我们的喜好装修
Is there such a place?
能找到吧？
Sure there is.
肯定能
So we should start looking for a condo you like?
那就开始找你喜欢的公寓吧？
What about you? Any preferences?
那你呢？有什么偏好吗？
Not really.
没什么特别的
No way.
不会吧
Nothing you want or hope for?
没有想要的东西吗？
I want a kitchen that is easy to use.
我想要一个实用的厨房
But it's the contents, not the package.
但那属于内部设施 不是外部结构
The soft content, not the hard details.
属于软件 不是硬件
It's not about the building but who I'm living with.
重要的不是房子 而是和谁住在一起
Husband.
老公
What?
怎么了？
-Husband. -What, Wife?
-老公 -怎么了 老婆？
Husband!
老公
What are you saying, Husband?
你说什么呢 老公？
BASED ON THE MANGA "1122" BY PEKO WATANABE
（根据渡边平子同名漫画改编）
1122: FOR A HAPPY MARRIAGE
《1122 好夫妻》
-Cheers.
-干杯
Maybe "cheers" wasn't the right thing.
这时候干杯可能不太合适
It's fine.
没关系
Today is the one-month anniversary of my divorce.
今天是我离婚一个月的纪念日
But to think it was Ichiko and Otoya.
居然是一子和二也
I was so shocked.
真是没想到
Can I ask why?
能问一下原因吗？
Was it related to us tempting you to go to the brothel?
和我们怂恿你去风俗馆有关系吗？
Tempting is a little--
说“怂恿”有点…
Not at all.
完全没关系
Then why?
那是为什么？
I didn't fall in love with someone else,
我没有喜欢上其他人
nor did I start to hate Otoyan.
也没有不喜欢二也
I still love him, even now.
我到现在仍然爱着他
It sounds like I'm glossing it over.
感觉我是在说漂亮话
But
但是
I got tired of my marriage.
我厌倦了我们的婚姻
So you'll be starting fertility treatment too.
是这样啊 一子也要开始接受生育治疗
Therefore, I wanted to talk to you
因为你们是成功案例
as someone who had a successful experience.
所以想向你取取经
SIX MONTHS AGO
（六个月前）
You know she hasn't given birth yet. So you plan to get a lot of treatment?
她还没生呢 你打算努力接受治疗吗？
If need be, yes.
如果有必要 我会的
Which clinic did you go to?
你们去的哪家诊所？
We tried a lot of different places and finally found Arakawa Clinic.
我们试了好多家 最后找到了荒川诊所
So you did it there.
所以你们是在那里做的
I heard it was like a factory. Was it?
我听说就像工厂一样 是真的吗？
Yeah, it felt like we were on a conveyor belt.
对 感觉就像上了传送带
For real? But it's a good clinic.
真的吗？但那家诊所很好吧
How long did it take and how much was it?
花了多长时间？多少钱？
If you're comfortable telling me.
如果你不介意我问的话
Including the breaks we took, it was about two years.
算上中间休息的时间 一共两年左右
The cost was about 2.5 million yen.
费用大概是250万日元
Wow. That's a lot.
真的好多钱
Well, it took a lot of time and money.
时间和金钱还是其次
But it took a lot more psychologically,
更难的是心理压力
especially for my wife.
尤其是我老婆
I'll be fine psychologically.
我心理承受力很强的
I've been doing my research and reading tons of blogs.
我做了好多研究 看了好多博客
I'm prepared for all of it.
我已经准备好了
Right, you are. Unlike my wife.
是啊 不愧是一子
Does your husband also want it as much as you?
你老公也像你一样干劲十足吗？
Don't "what" me.
你“嗯”什么
So my husband,
我老公
he probably does.
应该没问题
-Probably? -Yeah.
-“应该”？ -嗯
Isn't fertility treatment more of a burden on women?
生育治疗对女性来说 才是更大的负担吧？
But my husband understands that very well.
但我老公理解这一点
If I'm okay, he'll be okay too.
只要我没问题 他就没问题
I see. Then that's good.
哦 那就好
It's very difficult for a husband and wife to always be on the same page.
夫妻能保持步伐一致 真的很难得
I hope both of you won't stress yourselves out.
希望你们能顶住压力
Mrs. Aihara, I have your ovarian age test results.
相原女士 您的卵巢年龄测试结果出来了
Forty-two years old.
42岁
Your chances are low even with the right timing and artificial insemination.
即使能准确把握时机进行人工授精 您的成功几率仍然很低
We want to do IVF.
我们想做试管婴儿
A higher ovarian age indicates lower ovarian functions.
卵巢年龄越高 卵巢功能越弱
Understood.
我知道了
Then before we begin, let me warn you.
那在开始前 先给你几句忠告吧
Please prioritize your treatment above everything else.
请你们把治疗当作头等大事 慎重对待
Often, we'll tell you to come in the very next day
因为治疗是根据你的生理周期决定的
because the treatments are based on your cycle.
所以就诊日期通常只能提前一天通知
I can't treat you if you miss an appointment due to work.
如果你因为工作错过预约 那我可没法给你治
I understand.
知道了
Then we'll do a pelvic examination on you.
那你先去做一个盆腔检查
And for you, we need to analyze your sperm, so go to the collection room.
你去精液采集室 我们要检查一下精子状态
Okay.
好
-Thank you. -Sure.
-谢谢 -好
We'll be in your care.
拜托了
I can't get pregnant,
如果不能正常排卵
no matter how much sperm I'm injected with,
无论输入多少精子
if I'm not ovulating regularly.
我也没法怀孕
I heard the rumors.
我听说过传言
But it really took five and a half hours.
但确实用了五个半小时
There were a lot of people.
人很多
You could have gone home first.
你本可以先回家的
This is something we're doing together.
这是我们两个人的事
And I can't be with you at every appointment.
而且我没办法次次都陪你来
I hope it will go well.
希望能进展顺利
Yeah.
是啊
Let's not get our hopes up too high.
我们放松心态 别抱太大期望
I'm kind of tired.
我有点累了
Want to grab dinner somewhere?
找个地方吃饭吧？
Great idea.
好主意
What do you want to eat?
你想吃什么？
Something that will give me energy.
能让人恢复元气的食物
-Give you energy? -Meat?
-恢复元气？ -肉？
-Meat. -How about it?
-肉 -怎么样？
-Okay. -Okay?
-好呀 -好
Sorry, this test didn't show high levels of HCG.
很遗憾 HCG水平不高
So even a Grade 5AA blastocyst won't work.
连5AA级的囊胚也不行呀
Look, the grade is only for the embryo's appearance. Most of them are not viable.
是这样 等级只针对胚胎外观 其中大多数都无法存活
Feel free to go to another clinic if you don't like it.
不满意就去别的诊所
I didn't mean to criticize you.
我不是在抱怨
It's a misconception that a high grade will result in a pregnancy.
以为等级高就能怀孕 这是误解
It will only make things harder for you if you keep thinking like that.
如果抱着这种想法 只会让你自己吃苦头
Okay.
哦
SATO ART CLINIC DAIKANYAMA
（佐藤亚诊所代官山 4.0星）
A VERY GOOD DOCTOR
（医生特别好）
ARAKAWA LADIES CLINIC
（荒川女性诊所 4.8星）
I WAS ABLE TO GET PREGNANT AT 43
（我43岁 成功怀孕）
SO HAPPY I SWITCHED TO THIS CLINIC
（转到这家诊所真是转对了）
Should we change clinics?
我们要不要换家诊所？
Here you go. Herbal tea.
给 花草茶
Thanks.
谢谢
Changing clinics?
换诊所？
Yeah, the way he got mad at you wasn't good.
他那么凶你确实不好
Sorry I couldn't go with you.
抱歉我没能陪你去
It was just for the results anyway.
只是去拿结果而已
He was rude.
他很没礼貌
But three negatives in a row is…
但接连三次失败…
Ichiko.
小一
Why don't you pause the treatment for now?
先暂停治疗一阵子吧？
Pause? Why?
暂停？为什么？
We have enough money for another round.
我们的钱还够再做一轮
Plus we don't know how much longer I can still be treated.
再说也不知道 我还有多长时间可以接受治疗
We don't have the time to pause it.
现在可没时间暂停
We need to move on to our next step.
得继续进行下一步
But this clinic has really good reviews.
但这家诊所的评价特别好
Mrs. Aihara, your ovarian follicles have no eggs for this cycle.
相原女士 这个周期 您的卵泡没有释放卵子
Take the pill and let's start again.
把药吃了 我们重新开始
Yes.
好
So you're pausing treatments this cycle.
所以这个周期你要暂停治疗
Yeah. That's why I can do some work this month.
所以这个月我能接点活儿干
Ichiko.
小一
You've been sleeping in the tatami room,
你最近都在和室睡地铺
but wouldn't it be better if you slept on the bed?
睡在床上不是更好吗？
I'll sleep out here if you prefer to sleep alone.
如果你想一个人睡 我可以去睡地铺
You don't need to go out of your way.
不用麻烦了
I'm not going out of my way.
我并不觉得麻烦
Even dinner. This is really good but it's so expensive.
还有晚餐也是 好是好 但太贵了
You don't need to buy so much.
你不用买这么多
The treatment is expensive enough.
治疗已经够贵的了
You're right.
你说得对
It--
我…
I did buy a little too much.
我确实买得有点多
I'll take the leftovers for lunch. Eat whatever you like.
剩下的明天我带去当午饭 你捡喜欢的吃吧
I'm sorry.
对不起
You were just trying to help.
你只是想帮忙而已
Thank you.
谢谢你
Ichiko.
小一
Tell me if there is something I can do for you.
如果我能为你做些什么 请你告诉我
Thanks.
谢谢
You know, Ichiko.
对了 小一
I think we should have another talk.
我觉得我们应该再好好谈一次
About?
谈什么？
Our future.
我们的未来
Our marriage and having kids.
我们的婚姻 还有生孩子的事
Sorry, Otoyan.
对不起 二也
I have a deadline today.
我今天有工作必须完成
So I need to finish that.
我先去忙了
How about tomorrow?
那明天呢？
Okay.
好吧
Tomorrow is good.
明天可以
Then let's talk tomorrow.
那我们明天再谈
Then I'll take a bath and go to bed.
那我洗个澡先睡了
Don't work too hard, Ichiko.
别太辛苦了 小一
Got it.
知道了
I'm back.
我回来了
Welcome back.
你回来啦
Did you eat?
吃过了吗？
-Yeah, I ate. -Okay.
-吃过了 -哦
Want to have a drink while we talk? Sake?
想边谈边喝点酒吗？清酒？
No. Let's stay sober.
不了 还是清醒点好
Then I'll make tea.
那我泡点茶
Thanks.
谢谢
Well…
那个…
it's about what you said last time.
关于你上次说的话
I couldn't stop thinking about
我一直在想
what you said about moving on to the next step.
上次你说要继续进行下一步
Is there no next step…
如果没有孩子…
for us if we don't have a baby?
我们就没有“下一步”了吗？
I'll be happy if we can have one.
如果能有孩子当然很好
But
但是
even if we can't, I'll still be happy to be your husband.
就算没有孩子 能和你继续做夫妻 我还是很开心
I'm not against continuing the fertility treatment.
我不反对继续接受生育治疗
But you seem…
但你似乎…
to put too much faith into it.
有点太执着了
Otoyan.
二也
Yesterday…
昨天…
you said to tell you if there is anything you can do, right?
你说如果有什么能做的 就告诉你 对吧？
I did. Is there something I can do for you?
对啊 我有什么能为你做的吗？
So I…
我…
I thought about it this entire time.
从昨天起我就一直在想这个问题
Since yesterday.
一直在想
But…
但是…
I couldn't think of anything.
我想不出来
You're already doing enough.
你已经做得够多了
It doesn't have to be about the treatment. Anything is fine.
不一定是关于治疗 什么事都行
I know.
我知道
Thank you.
谢谢你
But I…
但是我…
can't think of anything I want
我想不出
to say to you…
还想对你说什么…
or anything I want you to do for me.
或者还需要你为我做什么
I think I am putting too much faith in the treatment.
我对治疗太过执着
Because I can no longer see a future
是因为我已经无法想象
with just the two of us.
只有我们两个人的未来
You mean being with me?
你是指我们两个一起生活？
Is that why we need to have a baby?
所以我们才需要孩子？
That is why…
所以说…
this marriage is too hard for me.
继续做夫妻对我来说太难了
Since when?
从什么时候起？
I don't know exactly.
具体什么时候我也不知道
But I thought
但我觉得
if we had a baby and became parents…
如果我们生个孩子 成了父母…
I could escape the pain of this marriage
我就可以摆脱婚姻的痛苦
and keep going as a family.
继续当一家人
That's what I thought.
我之前是这么想的
But it's not right to hang on to that kind of possibility, right?
但抱着这种莫须有的念想 是错误的 对吧？
Is it because I had an affair with your permission?
是因为我在你的默许下 出轨了吗？
That is why you don't trust me?
所以你不再信任我了？
No.
不是的
That might have been the trigger.
或许那是触发原因
But it's not the reason why.
但不是根本原因
It's also not because we stopped having sex.
也不是因为我们成了无性夫妻
And I didn't fall in love with someone else.
我也没有爱上其他人
Then what?
那是为什么？
Sorry. Keep talking.
抱歉 你继续说
You didn't do anything wrong.
你没有做错任何事
I'm the problem.
问题出在我身上
This marriage…
这段婚姻…
has become…
对我来说…
too heavy a burden for me.
已经变得太过沉重
I'm sorry for being so selfish.
对不起 我太自私了
Ichiko.
小一
Do you want…
你想…
to leave me?
离开我吗？
Yes.
是的
This is not a decision…
那你这个决定…
you made quickly,
是经过了深思熟虑
on a whim, right?
不是因为一时冲动？
I understand.
我懂了
I understand, but…
我懂了 但是…
Give me some time.
给我点时间
I understand how serious you are about this.
我知道在这件事上你有多认真了
I said it.
我说出来了
I really said it.
真的说出来了
Otoyan gave me his answer two days later.
二也两天后给了我答复
That weekend,
那个周末
on a beautiful, clear autumn day,
一个秋高气爽的日子
a morning in the seventh year of our marriage.
我们结婚第七年的一个早晨
Here you go.
麻烦您了
Divorce papers, correct?
离婚登记吗？
We submitted our divorce papers
我们提交了离婚申请
and put an end
结束了
to our married life.
这段婚姻
DIVORCE REGISTRATION OCTOBER 12, 2024
（离婚登记 2024年10月12日）
That is what happened.
就是这样
Say something.
你们说话呀
Well…
唉呀…
I can talk shit about him
如果他是个坏老公的话
and congratulate you if he was a horrible husband.
我可以说他一堆坏话 恭喜你离婚
But I somehow can't with Otoya.
但二也不是这种人
-Yeah. -Right?
-是啊 -对吧？
He made a really good Chinese tea for me when I was hungover at Ichiko's place.
我在一子家宿醉那次 他帮我泡过很高级的中国茶
-That's a good husband experience. -Yeah.
-真是好老公啊 -嗯
Otoyan is really good at taking care of people.
二也真的很会照顾人
Hey, Yuri. Tell her how good it is to be single.
小玉 告诉她当单身贵族有多好
You can give it your all in love and work.
你可以尽情谈恋爱 全身心投入工作
That was like you copied it from an old show.
好老掉牙的台词哦
-You told me to say good things. -Anyway--
-是你让我夸单身好的 -好啦…
Thank you. But aside from work,
谢谢你们 但除了工作
I have no interest in love right now.
我现在对谈恋爱不感兴趣
I'll focus on enjoying being alone first.
我想先尽情享受一下单身生活
Now the married ladies should say words of support.
现在已婚女士们应该说几句鼓励的话
-Now. Come on. -What?
-来啊 -什么啊？
Well…
那…
Is there anything?
有吗？
Isn't now a good time to sell your home? You're in a nice neighborhood.
正好趁这个机会把公寓卖了吧？ 环境位置那么好
-That? -Property distribution is important.
-这事？ -财产分割很重要
Yeah.
对
-That's right. -Well, marriage is one form of love.
-说得对 -婚姻是一种爱的形式
And you can break up if it becomes too difficult.
如果变得太困难 可以分手
Ichiko can't tell a lie anyway.
一子肯定不会说谎
Yeah, but now that I'm single,
但现在单身了
I feel that I am finally seeing my true self
我感觉终于看清了自己
since I've been relying on Otoyan so much.
以前我对二也太依赖了
Your true self is important.
看清自己很重要的
Congratulations for finding your true self.
恭喜你终于找到了真正的自我
You can give it your all in love and work.
你可以全身心地工作、恋爱啦
Hey.
喂
-Let's drink.
-喝酒
-Congratulations.
-恭喜
Thank you.
谢谢
We might have congratulated you, but we're all very worried about you, you know?
虽然大家都恭喜你 但其实我们很担心你哦
I know.
我知道
You tend to not show it to your friends when you're having a hard time.
你遇到困难时 一般不会让朋友们看出来
Really?
会吗？
I think I talked about it a lot.
感觉我谈了很多呀
I think you've only shown Otoya
我觉得这么多年来
what you're really feeling and thinking all these years.
你只对二也坦露过心扉
You think so?
是吗？
Yeah, I do.
是啊
It's because Otoyan was like another me.
因为二也就像另一个我
Now I have to…
现在我必须…
slowly learn to open myself up to other people.
慢慢学会对其他人打开心扉
You think I can do it?
你觉得我能做到吗？
Of course.
肯定可以
You'll be one of them.
包括你在内
Okay.
好呀
Hug.
抱一个
Hug?
抱一个？
-Hug. -Squeeze.
-抱抱 -用力
You did your best.
你尽力了
Hello? Otoyan?
喂？二也
Ichiko, it's me.
小一 是我
I'm too busy this week so I can't pick up the rest of my things.
我这周太忙 没时间来拿剩下的东西
Can you send them to me? I'll pay on delivery.
你可以帮我寄过来吗？邮费我出
Got it.
好的
And…
还有…
Ichiko.
小一
Did you tell your mother we got divorced?
我们离婚的事 你告诉你妈妈了吗？
Not yet.
还没
I was thinking about telling her soon.
我打算这两天告诉她
I won't say anything to her.
我不会跟她说的
But I'm worried because she hasn't responded to my message.
但我有点担心 最近发的短信她都没回
She usually responds right away.
她一般回复很快
I got it.
知道了
I'll contact her.
我会联系她的
Then, good night.
那好 晚安
Good night.
晚安
Slowly but surely,
慢慢地
I am becoming alone…
二也的痕迹在逐渐消失
as traces of Otoyan get erased.
孤单的感觉变得分外真切
JR EAST
（JR东日本 本纳站）
I'm home.
我回来了
Mom?
妈妈？
Mom.
妈妈
Are you dead?
你死了吗？
The expression my mom had in her final moments alone
妈妈孤身一人 最后留下的表情
was the complete opposite of the word "peaceful."
和“安详”完全不沾边
It was one where I can easily imagine how painful it was.
我能想象出她当时有多痛苦
I swore to never forget it.
我发誓要牢记这一幕
Because I felt…
因为我觉得…
my own end
我自己咽气时
would also look like that.
也会是这副模样
WHITE BAMBI
（白斑比）
Hello? Ichiko?
喂？小一
Hello, Otoyan?
喂？二也
Sorry for calling you at work.
抱歉打扰你工作了
What's up?
怎么了？
My mother passed away.
我妈去世了
I found her at home yesterday.
我昨天在家里找到她的
So, she didn't respond to my message because…
所以她不回短信是因为…
I asked the hospital to examine her,
我让医院做了尸检
and they said she died two days ago.
他们说她是两天前走的
Probably from a heart attack.
可能是心肌梗塞
I see.
这样啊
Ichiko, are you all right?
小一 你没事吧？
I'm okay.
我没事
I wanted to let you know since you had taken care of her.
我就想告诉你一声 因为你之前很照顾她
Thank you.
谢谢你
Ichiko.
小一
Where are you now?
你现在在哪儿？
Now?
现在？
At her house.
在我妈家
Alone?
就你一个人？
Alone.
我一个人
Can you handle everything on your own?
你能应付得来吗？
Yeah, don't worry. I'll keep things simple.
没关系 我会一切从简
I can do it if I talk to the funeral home and do some research online.
我可以问殡仪馆 再上网查查
Yeah, I also need mourning clothes.
还得准备丧服
I'll just buy them around here.
在附近买就行了
Ichiko.
小一
I'll come to you.
我过来陪你
Otoyan, don't you have work tomorrow?
那你明天不用工作吗？
That is what paid leave is for.
我刚好有带薪假期
So wait for me.
等着我啊
Bye.
再见
Otoyan.
二也
Hi, Ichiko.
你好啊 小一
I got you a snack.
我给你带了吃的
Thanks.
谢谢
You'll be the chief mourner, right?
葬礼会由你主持吧？
Then I'll make the arrangements with the funeral home as your husband.
那我就以你丈夫的身份 去殡仪馆安排葬礼的事
You can check the important details later.
之后你再把重要细节过一遍就行
So you should just rest.
这样你就能好好休息了
You haven't slept for two days, right?
你两天没睡了吧？
-But-- -It's okay.
-可是… -没关系的
There will be a lot of things only family members can do and decide on.
有很多事只有家人才能做决定办理
It was like that when my dad died.
我父亲过世时就是这样
So let me do what I can.
让我尽些绵薄之力吧
Then the wake and funeral will be on this date.
那守灵和下葬就定在这一天
Yes.
好
Do you have any questions or concerns?
您还有什么问题或者顾虑吗？
We still don't know how many people will come.
我们还不知道会有多少人来参加
What should I do about how much food to order?
订餐的事怎么决定呢？
You don't need to decide that right now.
那个不用现在就决定
You can inform us once you know.
等确定了再通知我们就行
Great.
好
And how should we order the flowers for the altar?
另外 祭坛的鲜花怎么订购？
For example, if a relative wants to give a flower arrangement,
假如有亲戚想送花篮
is there a specific florist…
有没有哪家花店…
-Right? -Yes, I was so surprised to hear.
-是吧？ -是啊 我听说时特别惊讶
She was so healthy.
她平时身体那么好
We'll be going now.
我们告辞了
Okay. Take care.
保重
Thank you for coming.
谢谢你们专程赶来
You came even though we're divorced.
虽然我们已经不是夫妻了
Nothing has changed for us.
对我们来说 什么都没有变
Hey, if it's not a problem,
如果可以的话
you should stay with her today, Otoya.
今天你应该留下陪她 二也
If Ichiko is okay with it.
如果小一愿意
What do you say, Ichiko?
你说呢 小一？
Then, please…
那就麻烦你了
Ichiko.
小一
Be sure to rest well.
一定要注意身体
You can make Otoya do all the work.
你可以把事情都交给二也去做
Thank you.
谢谢
I really appreciate it.
我真的很感激
It's the house making noises.
是房子的声音
It's really loud.
真响啊
I wonder if Mom is angry…
也许妈妈生气了…
since I was a bad daughter.
因为我是个坏女儿
Of course she has a grudge against me.
她当然会恨我
That's not true.
不会的
You were always thinking about your mother.
你一直很担心你妈妈
Otoyan.
二也
Can I come over to your side?
我能挪过去挨着你吗？
You know…
说起来…
I didn't shed a single tear
妈妈去世的时候
when my mom died.
我一滴眼泪都没流
That was cold-hearted, even for me.
我真够冷血的
I can't say I understand.
我不能说我理解
Crying isn't the only way to express your sadness.
但哭泣并不是表达悲伤的唯一方式
I think everyone shows their sadness at different times
我觉得每个人表达悲伤的时机和方式
and in different ways.
都是不同的
How sad a person is
一个人的悲伤程度
can't be measured by how they show it or by what they do.
不能用他表现出的状态衡量
Ichiko.
小一
Did you see the box on top of the toaster in the kitchen?
你看到厨房里 烤面包机上的盒子了吗？
What?
什么盒子？
The box for the kettle I bought…
我买给你妈妈的热水壶…
for your mom was stacked on top.
包装盒还堆在上面
It was unopened.
没有拆封
That time,
那时候
I knew…
我就知道…
what your mom wanted…
你妈妈想要的…
wasn't a fancy kettle.
并不是高级水壶
I kind of knew it.
我感觉到了
But I didn't have the time.
但当时我没时间
So I did something that made her feel lonely.
我做了让她感到孤独的事
I made it hard for her to say anything…
送了她一个水壶
by sending her that kettle.
让她不好开口
I really liked your mom, you know.
我真的很喜欢你妈妈
She wasn't good at expressing herself.
她不善于表达自己
But she was honest and strong.
但她诚实、坚强
I'm not hurting as much as you.
我的悲痛无法与你相比
But I think I can share your grief.
但我们可以一起哀悼她
Mom, I'm so sorry.
妈妈 对不起
Then,
好了
thank you for everything, Otoyan.
真的非常感谢 二也
Take good care of yourself, Ichiko.
好好照顾自己 小一
Bye.
再见
-Sorry. -I'm sorry.
-抱歉 -对不起
Are you okay?
你没事吧？
I need to be the one to turn around…
必须由我转身离去
because my ex-husband
因为我的前夫
is too kind.
太善良了
I'm home.
我回来了
Some time after that,
过了一段时间
I called Otoyan and we decided
我给二也打电话
to sell our home.
我们决定把公寓卖掉
I continued living here
在找到买家之前
alone,
我继续一个人
until we found a buyer.
在那里生活
Coming.
来了
THREE MONTHS LATER
（三个月后）
-Hello. -Hi.
-你好
-Thank you. -Nice to meet you.
-谢谢 -很高兴见到你
-We'll take a look around.
-打扰了
-Thank you. -Of course.
-谢谢 -没事
-Thanks for letting us come. -Please come in.
-谢谢 打扰了 -请进
Three months later,
三个月后
someone wanted to buy the condo.
有人想买这套公寓
So I called Otoyan so we can meet them together.
于是我打给二也 看房那天让他也过来
Pardon the intrusion.
打扰了
Thank you for having us.
谢谢 打扰了
It has good sunlight.
这儿光线很好
The windows face southeast so you get sun for most of the day.
窗户朝向东南 所以一天中大部分时间都有光照
It's rare for such a good home to be available in this neighborhood.
这片小区里难得有这样的好房子
-That's true. -Yes.
-确实 -是啊
Looking at it in person, it looks much newer than it actually is.
实际看到以后 感觉好新 都不像老房子
We did a lot of renovations.
我们做了很多装修
-Really? -I see.
-是吗？ -这样啊
Look, aren't the tiles in the kitchen cute?
你看 厨房的瓷砖是不是很可爱？
Yeah.
确实
Now that I'm seeing them up close, they aren't smooth and have some texture.
现在靠近看 才发现上面有花纹 不是平的
That's right.
对啊
I shopped around to find them.
我找了很多家才买到的
They're really cute.
真的很可爱
Is it hard to keep a tiled kitchen clean?
厨房里铺瓷砖会不会难清洁？
It's really easy. You can just wipe it off.
清洁起来很方便的 一擦就行
Tomato sauce won't stain it even if it splatters.
哪怕沾上番茄酱也能擦掉
That's nice.
真方便
The grout is black too. You could see the stains if it was white.
瓷砖缝也是黑的 白色的比较不耐脏
That's what they said when I bought the tiles.
我买瓷砖时 他们也这么说
They told us black is better if we cook often.
他们说如果我们常做饭 黑色比较实用
I have a question.
可以问个问题吗？
What is it?
什么问题？
Why do you want to sell this place?
你们为什么想卖掉这套公寓？
I was wondering if there were any cons of living here.
我在想住在这里会不会有什么缺点
I want to ask just in case.
我想问一下 以防万一
-Right? -Yeah. You're right.
-对吧？ -对 有道理
I don't have any complaints about it.
我对这里没有什么不满意的
But it's not the hard details, but the soft contents.
但重要的不是硬件 而是软件
It's not about the building, but who you'll be living with.
不是公寓 而是一起生活的人
Why don't we take a look at the tatami room?
我们去看一下榻榻米房间吧？
-Sure. -This way, please.
-好 -请跟我来
Ichiko.
小一
Ichiko, are you okay?
小一 你没事吧？
I'm sorry.
对不起
I can't
我果然不能
sell this place after all.
把这里卖了
What?
什么？
I'm sorry.
对不起
I'm really sorry. You even came all the way here.
真的很抱歉 还麻烦你们大老远赶来
Here.
给你
Thanks.
谢谢
Are you out of sugar?
家里没糖了？
No, I still have some.
不啊 还有的
I bought some a few days ago.
我几天前刚买过
Really? I didn't see it.
是吗？我怎么没看到
Really?
是吗？
I just used it though.
我刚用过
Right.
好吧
How come it fell?
怎么会掉下来？
I was busy with work right until--
我之前一直在忙工作…
-Ouch! -Ouch.
-好疼 -疼
That hurts, Ichiko.
好疼啊 小一
-Sorry. -It's okay.
-对不起 -没关系
I was working right until they came.
我一直工作到看房前最后一刻
So I cleaned in a hurry. Are you okay, Otoyan?
所以打扫得很匆忙 你没事吧 二也？
Yeah.
没事
So I put it there…
我就塞那儿了…
-Sugar… -Yeah?
-砂糖… -嗯？
…won't grow mold if you put it in an air-tight container.
…放进真空罐里才不会受潮
I'll put it in the old container.
放在这个旧瓶子里就行
So there was a reason for that.
原来是有原因的呀
I thought you put it in a bottle because it looked nice.
我还以为放瓶子里是为了美观
You really have it together, don't you?
你真的好有条理
You think so?
是吗？
I'll take my tea with sugar today too.
今天我也要在茶里加糖
Okay.
好
Crying makes you tired, right?
哭完觉得累吧？
Here.
给
Thanks.
谢谢
Are you tired too?
你也累了吗？
because I was nervous.
因为之前很紧张
I kept thinking about how sad I'd feel
我一直在想如果看房的人
if the people viewing our place said they would buy it,
决定要买下来 我会有多难过
even though we both decided to sell it.
虽然这是我俩共同的决定
But when it actually happened,
但真来人看房了
I thought about emphasizing how hard it is to open and close the window screens.
我就想着强调纱窗有多难开关
Like how much the sun burns the tatami mats.
太阳会把榻榻米晒得特别烫
Yeah. And that the closet door creaks.
对啊 还有衣柜的门会吱嘎作响
Sometimes the kitchen drawers won't close.
有时候厨房抽屉会关不上
The bathroom door mysteriously opens by itself in the winter.
冬天里浴室门会莫名其妙地自动打开
And when it rains,
还有下雨时
-the living room doorknob gets stuck. -The living room doorknob gets stuck.
-客厅的门把手会卡住
But
但话说回来
I didn't think they would like this place so quickly
我没想到他们会一眼就看上这里
since it's a pretty old building.
毕竟这栋楼有些年头了
I got used to looking at the kitchen tiles,
厨房的瓷砖我看惯了不觉得
but they are very cute.
但真的很好看
Now, the hard details are a mess, and the soft contents have separated.
现在硬件都乱七八糟 软件也各奔东西了
But…
但是…
is it okay if I want to start over?
如果我想从新开始 可不可以呢？
Sorry for being selfish.
对不起 是我太自私了
I…
我…
thought we couldn't be together if we weren't married or didn't have kids.
以前觉得如果不是夫妻 或者没有孩子 我们就不能在一起
But I…
但我…
don't want to give up on our relationship.
不想放弃我们的感情
Those are…
这是我的…
my true feelings.
真心话
Ichiko.
小一
To tell you the truth…
老实说…
when I saw you crying…
刚才看到你哭了…
and saying you didn't want to sell…
说你不想卖房…
I was so incredibly happy.
我真的好开心
I'm really happy…
我太开心了…
the home we built together…
不用失去…
won't be gone anymore.
我们俩一起打造的家
MIDORI OSTEOPATHY
（绿色整骨）
Since you will increase the types of treatments you provide for women,
因为要拓宽针对女性的服务
you want to renew your website.
所以你想更新网站
Yes.
是的
I'll help improve their basic problems and support their health and beauty.
我会帮助女性解决根本问题 让她们变得更加健康美丽
My services will include pressure therapy, pelvic realignment and diet consultation.
服务项目将包括压力疗法 骨盆调整和饮食咨询
I want to connect it to improving femininity and maternal instincts.
希望能和提高女性气质、母性方面挂钩
-Want to give it a try? -What?
-想试试看吗？ -咦？
What do you mean "what"? You don't have kids yet, right?
“咦”什么“咦” 你还没生小孩吧？
You shouldn't be so indecisive.
别再犹豫不决了
Didn't I tell you? Your energy levels will start to drop.
我不是说过嘛？体力会一年不如一年
I won't have children.
我不会有孩子
You shouldn't give up on having kids.
放弃生孩子 那可不行啊
That's not what I meant.
我不是那个意思
Then what did you mean?
那你什么意思？
I'm just really happy right now.
我现在很幸福
So I'm good.
所以没关系
But I'd like to learn more about the pelvic realignment.
不过我对骨盆调整很感兴趣
I think there is a big need for it since more people are working from home.
我觉得这项治疗会很受欢迎 因为现在好多人在家办公
-Right? Isn't that right? -Yes.
-对吧？是这样没错吧？ -对
The younger people need it, right?
年轻人需要 对吧？
I think they need it because they are young.
对年轻人特别有必要
-Because? -Yes.
-是吧？ -嗯
It smells so nice.
好香啊
Right? It has a great scent.
对吧？真好闻
-Wow. -Amazing.
太香了
-It does. -What a flower.
-是啊 -这花真香
Everyone.
各位
We'll be using the cape jasmine today.
今天用到的是栀子花
One stalk alone can be a work of art.
仅仅一枝就能成为一件艺术品
I want you all to think about using it in a bold arrangement.
希望大家大胆创作
By the way, the flower language for cape jasmine is…
对了 栀子花的花语是…
MIDORI OSTEOPATHY
（绿色疗法）
KEEP THE BEIGE BACKGROUND ASK FOR NEW PHOTOS
（保留米色背景 要新照片）
I'm back.
我回来了
Welcome back.
你回来啦
-Working? -Yeah.
-在工作？ -嗯
You're in a good mood.
你心情不错嘛
You can tell?
看出来啦？
That smells nice. Is it the flower?
好香啊 是花吗？
What kind of flower?
是什么花？
Cape jasmine.
栀子花
Why a bouquet?
为什么是花束？
Here.
送给你
You won't arrange it?
不插起来吗？
THIS IS A WORK OF FICTION.
（本故事纯属虚构）
Subtitle: Annie Chen
字幕翻译：纪小敏